<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vnrighteovs Mammon exchanged for the true riches or A sermon, preached at the funeral of William Adams Esq; in the parish church of St. Lawrence Iury on Tuesday. Septemb. 3. 1661. By Thomas Horton. D.D.</title>
            <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826121</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826121</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1760:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vnrighteovs Mammon exchanged for the true riches or A sermon, preached at the funeral of William Adams Esq; in the parish church of St. Lawrence Iury on Tuesday. Septemb. 3. 1661. By Thomas Horton. D.D.</title>
                  <author>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by I.R. for John CLark, and are to be sold at the entrance into Mercers Chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Adams, William, 1594-1661 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNRIGHTEOVS MAMMON EXCHANGED FOR THE TRUE RICHES OR A SERMON, Preached at the Funeral of <hi>William Adams</hi> Eſq; In the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Lawrence Iury</hi> on Tueſday. Septemb. 3. 1661.</p>
            <p>BY THOMAS HORTON. D. D.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 112.5.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A <hi>Good Man</hi> ſheweth mercy, and lendeth: He wil guide his affaires with <hi>Diſcretion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He hath diſperſed abroad, He hath given to the poor, his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe remaineth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. R.</hi> for <hi>John Clark,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Entrance into <hi>Mercers Chappel.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30513:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30513:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull, The Maſter, Wardens, and Aſſiſtants Of the Company of HABERDASHERS IN LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull, and much Honoured in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing requeſted by the Friends of this worthy <hi>Citizen,</hi> and <hi>Brother</hi> of your <hi>Company</hi> now lately deceaſed, to put this Sermon in to print, which was preach'd at his interrment, I knew not to whom more properly to dedicate and intitle it, then to <hi>your ſelves;</hi> who being made the <hi>Trustees</hi> for that <hi>Bounty</hi> which he hath left behind him, might be alſo the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of thoſe Truths which are aſſerted of Him, and applyed unto Him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scripture</hi> which is here handled, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be every way ſuitable and agreeable to the preſent <hi>Occaſion:</hi> which firſt being a <hi>Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> hath therefore in it the ſeaſonable remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of <hi>Death</hi> and final diſſolution, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations for another World. And then being the Funeral of a perſon whom God had bleſt with a very fair &amp; plentifull <hi>Eſtate,</hi> hath likewiſe in it the pertinent mention of this worldly and earthly <hi>Mammon,</hi> and the Riches of this preſent
<pb facs="tcp:30513:3"/>life. And laſtly, being the Funeral of a <hi>Bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and Liberal Perſon, and of one that had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of his Eſtate in a Charitable Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath accordingly in it Directions to <hi>make Friends of this Mammon of unrighteouſneſs</hi> to the beſt and moſt deſirable Advantage.</p>
            <p>Now the main ſcope and end of ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes as theſe are, is that thoſe who are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them might in ſome ſort be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to them, and have them wrought as it were into themſelves. This I look upon as that which is more particularly <hi>Your</hi> Opportunity, from that <hi>Work</hi> wherein you are ingaged for the managing of this <hi>Perſons</hi> Liberality. I know not how it comes to paſs, but mens <hi>ſpirits</hi> doe uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and for the moſt part partake of their <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</hi> Thoſe, who are taken up in low and meaner ſervices, they have commonly a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit ingendred &amp; contracted by them. Whereas Noble and Generous Performances beget noble and Generous <hi>Affections,</hi> and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Perſons which are intereſted &amp; concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them into the very nature of the things themſelves. Upon which account it is much to be hoped, that as many of you as God hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with abilities anſwerable thereunto, in
<pb facs="tcp:30513:3"/>this diſcharge of a Truſt for another, you will your ſelves be unawares drawn into a comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with ſo good an example, as is here ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for you. At leaſt, that you will ſo order and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of this Charity of <hi>His,</hi> as in a manner to make it <hi>your own,</hi> &amp; thereby to make to your ſelves ſo many Friends of this <hi>Mammon of Righteouſneſs,</hi> which you may do at the <hi>ſecond hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Heart</hi> of man by nature is ſo deſperately treacherous &amp; <hi>deceitfull,</hi> where it is not rectified by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> and a ſpecial <hi>watchfulneſs</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it ſelf, as that from hence there are great <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes</hi> and miſcarriages oftentimes in the world in ſuch matters as theſe are; both for the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the works of Charity in men's own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, as alſo for the <hi>Executing</hi> of the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of other men; which yet is no diſparagement at all to the works themſelves ſimply conſider'd being ſtill the ſame in their own nature, nor yet any reflexion upon ſuch perſons as are <hi>really</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable in them who ſhall notwithſtanding reap the fruit of their own Integrity. But it is that which may awaken all men very narrowly to look into themſelves, and to examine their own ſoules in this particular. Becauſe <hi>othervviſe</hi> they may give not onely <hi>half</hi> but <hi>all</hi> their Goods
<pb facs="tcp:30513:4"/>to the feeding of the poor, and yet be <hi>void of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> and may likewiſe be thought in ſome ſort to diſcharge their <hi>Trust,</hi> and yet not to diſcharge their <hi>Conſciences.</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> in this very chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and upon this very occaſion it ſelf tells the Phariſees whom he converſt withall, that <hi>They were ſuch as juſtified themſelves before men, but that God knew their Hearts;</hi> for <hi>THAT WHICH IS HIGHLY ESTEEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED AMONGST MEN, IS ABOMINATION IN THE SIGHT OF GOD.</hi> The better that any thing is of it's own nature wherein we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, the more need have we to look to our Mindes &amp; Affections in the managing of it, that ſo we may not <hi>miſcarry</hi> in that, wherein we ſeem to <hi>triumph,</hi> and moſt to glory and pride our ſelves. Which that it may be the better avoided in this preſent buſineſs in hand (as in all others beſides) it is worth the while for men to enquire into their ſtate &amp; Condition in <hi>Grace;</hi> and the conſtant and general frame &amp; temper of their own Hearts, there being nothing done as it ſhould be, which does not flow from ſuch a Principle as this. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> again in the following words makes this ſober and ſerious Expoſtulation, <hi>If ye be not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in that which is ANOTHER man's, who ſhall give you that which is your OWNE?</hi> we may a little <hi>invert</hi> it,
<pb facs="tcp:30513:4"/>and turn it <hi>thus;</hi> If ye be not faithfull in that which is your <hi>Own,</hi> who ſhall truſt you with that which is <hi>another</hi> man's? There is no man can ever be a <hi>Good</hi> Husband for <hi>Others</hi> that is a <hi>Bad</hi> Husband for <hi>Himſelf;</hi> and he that neglects the Care of his own <hi>Soul,</hi> can never be a good <hi>Truſtee</hi> for another's <hi>Eſtate.</hi> Religion is an <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> buſineſs, and conſiſtent to it ſelf: Men may carry it perhaps <hi>plauſibly</hi> and gloriouſly in the Eyes of the World, and <hi>make a fair shew in the flesh</hi> for a little <hi>time;</hi> but every man will have ſo much Comfort at <hi>last,</hi> as he hath <hi>ſinceritie</hi> in him, and a <hi>ſpirit in vvhich is no guile.</hi> When God ſhall come to <hi>Iudgement,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall ſit upon his laſt <hi>Tribunal,</hi> (as he one day <hi>vvill</hi>) He will then call men to Account for <hi>Affections,</hi> as well as for <hi>Actions,</hi> and for the <hi>Principles</hi> of doing, as well as for the <hi>Things</hi> themſelves, which have bin done by them; and then ſhall every one have <hi>Praiſe,</hi> or <hi>Blame</hi> from <hi>Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things I doe not ſuggeſt, as any way ſuſpecting your <hi>Selves,</hi> who have given ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Teſtimony of your Fidelity in things of this nature by former experiences: Nor yet as in the leaſt reflecting upon the <hi>Example</hi> here preſented unto you, whom I have looked upon
<pb facs="tcp:30513:5"/>as a Perſon of as great Integrity in this Buſineſs as any man elſe. But onely as taking occaſion from the Opportunity which is here afforded to diſcourſe of the Point <hi>at large,</hi> and to expreſs my thoughts about it in a <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Theological</hi> Diſcuſſion. I have nothing further but my <hi>Prayers</hi> that God would ſet home the Truths here mention'd upon the <hi>Hearts</hi> of all thoſe that are partakers of them, and that he would ſend forth <hi>many</hi> ſuch Perſons out of your renowned and flouriſhing <hi>Societie,</hi> as may be inrich'd with the like <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and the like <hi>Hearts;</hi> which is the earneſt and unfeigned Deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your SERVANT for the <hi>True Riches,</hi> And, Your FRIEND for the <hi>Everlaſting Habitations.</hi> Thomas Horton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30513:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke XVI. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And I ſay unto you; Make unto your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, that when ye faile, they may receive you into everlaſting Habitations.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which hath bin wont ſometimes to be ſaid of a <hi>good wit,</hi> it is more eſpecially and properly true of a <hi>good heart:</hi> that it is able to <hi>make uſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing,</hi> and to improve it to its own advantage; not only in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of virtue, by conforming to that whch is <hi>abſolutely</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> good in <hi>them;</hi> but likewiſe in the examples of <hi>Iniquity</hi> by picking out that which is <hi>occaſionally</hi> and <hi>circumſtantially</hi> good in <hi>them alſo.</hi> An inſtance whereof we have here in this Scripture, which we have now before us in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the <hi>unjuſt Steward</hi> mentioned in the beginning of this chapter; whoſe providence and forecaſt for Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt the time of his expected <hi>ejection</hi> out of his <hi>Stewardſhip</hi> (though by ſinful and unlawful meanes) is improved by our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> as a pattern to all <hi>rich</hi> Perſons to provide for their <hi>ſoules</hi> againſt the time of their expected <hi>diſsolution</hi> and departure out of this world: but in a way far more warrantable, though in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30513:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſutable thereunto; &amp; that is, by <hi>making to themſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs, that ſo when they fail, they may receive them into everlasting habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words themſelves there are three general Parts conſiderable: <hi>firſt</hi> the quickning <hi>Preface</hi> or authoritative <hi>Introduction,</hi> I ſay unto you. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The ſober <hi>advice</hi> or ſerious counſel following upon it, <hi>Make unto your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſs. Thirdly,</hi> The perſuaſive <hi>Argument</hi> or Ground for the practiſe of it, <hi>That when ye fail they may receive you into everlaſting habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We begin with the <hi>former, viz.</hi> The quickning <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> or Introduction, <hi>I ſay unto you,</hi> This is a form of ſpeech which our Saviour Chriſt does often uſe in his diſcourſes, eſpecially in ſuch buſineſſes as are of more weighty and ſerious conſideration, or where the minds of his hearers are not altogether ſo quick and attentive; Here he does uſually excite, and ſtir them up from the thoughts and apprehenſions of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> whom they have to deal withal, that ſo they may take heed leaſt <hi>they refuſe him that ſpeaketh,</hi> who ſhould moſt effectually prevaile with them. And theres a twofold intimation in it to make it ſo much the more efficacious; Firſt of <hi>Skil</hi> and underſtanding, I that <hi>Know</hi> what I ſay. Secondly, of <hi>Love</hi> and affection, I that ſpeak it out of my <hi>good will</hi> unto you. Where there is a concurrence of theſe two; an <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> ſpeaker and an <hi>Affectionate,</hi> there's very great cauſe for liſtning and <hi>attending</hi> to him: and ſo it is <hi>here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. There's his <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>underſtanding;</hi> He is not one that ſpeaks at randome he knows not what; but with a great deal of wiſdome, and diſcretion, ſo great as that none the like, <hi>Never any man ſpake as he ſpake.</hi> And that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30513:6"/>as to knowledge and judgement. He knows all kind of Natures and Perſons and Actions and Events. His <hi>Name</hi> is <hi>Counſellour,</hi> And ſo he is fitteſt to <hi>adviſe</hi> his people for his <hi>wisdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. For his <hi>Love and affection,</hi> ther's much conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in <hi>that</hi> alſo; there are many, who can ſpeak admirable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and give very good Counſel in regard of that which comes from them; but it may be they have ſome ſiniſter <hi>End,</hi> or unworthy deſign in it: but for <hi>Chriſt</hi> what he ſpeakes, it is in ſincerity and out of <hi>good will</hi> to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom he ſpeaks, But this I doe not inſiſt upon, as haſtening to that which is mainly and principally intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thats the <hi>Firſt General, viz.</hi> The quickning <hi>Preface,</hi> or Introduction, <hi>I ſay unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the ſober <hi>Advice or Council</hi> which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows upon it in theſe words; <hi>Make to your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> wherein again we have two branches more. Firſt, the <hi>thing</hi> adviſed to, and that is the <hi>making of friends.</hi> Secondly, The <hi>meanes</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to for the effecting and accompliſhing of this thing, and that is to do it by the <hi>Mammon of unrightuouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Firſt,</hi> the thing it ſelf adviſed to, it is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt to be the <hi>making of friends;</hi> This will be the more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable; if we ſhall conſider the <hi>quality</hi> of the Perſons, to whom theſe words are directed: and that is (as appears by the <hi>ſcope</hi> of them) to <hi>rich</hi> men, ſuch perſons as have an abundance of theſe worldly goods by them, theſe are <hi>they</hi> who are heere call'd upon to the <hi>making of friends to themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtay, what need have theſe of friends? thoſe that have wealth and riches and a fulneſs of theſe outward poſſeſſions, they can ſhift well enough of themſelves and<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30513:7"/>be their <hi>own</hi> friends, though they had none elſe to regard them or look after them; yea indeed ſometimes they <hi>think</hi> ſo and are lifted up with ſuch thoughts as theſe are: well, but for all that, ſayes our Saviour do <hi>you</hi> make your friends; you which are rich and wealthy perſons, ſuch as theſe have need of friends, as well as any man elſe, yea and they have need to <hi>make</hi> friends too; theres <hi>that</hi> alſo in the text, <hi>make</hi> to your ſelves friends. As for <hi>poor</hi> men indeed, we are apt to think with our ſelves that ſuch as they have need to make friends, becauſe they have ſo many Enemies. <hi>All the Brethren of the poor hate him, how much more doe his friends go farr off from him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he purſueth them with words, yet they are wanting to him.</hi> Pro. 19.7. And again Pro. 14.20. <hi>The poor is hated even of his own neighbour,: but the rich hath many friends.</hi> Or <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the Lovers of the rich,</hi> as it is in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> text, <hi>Rich</hi> men (as one would think) they have friends enow <hi>made to their hands</hi> from the Nature of their condition: well, but yet ſtill for all this, have theſe (I ſay) need to make friends: and <hi>Christ himſelf</hi> ſayes it alſo, yea they have need to make friends of the <hi>pooreſt</hi> and meaneſt people that are, as having great uſe of them. God hath in his infinite wiſdome and providence, ſo ordered and diſpoſed it, that no ſorts of men ſhould be <hi>abſolute</hi> or <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> one upon another but that they ſhould be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually helpful &amp; beneficial. The <hi>rich</hi> do as much need the <hi>poor,</hi> as the poor the <hi>rich:</hi> and they cannot ſay unto them <hi>wee have no need of you,</hi> no more then the <hi>members of the body</hi> one to another 1 Cor. 12.21. <hi>Dives &amp; pauper duo ſibi ſunt Contraria: ſed &amp; iterum duo ſibi ſunt neceſsaria</hi> ſayes St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> the <hi>rich and the poor</hi> they are two <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30513:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to one another, but yet they are two <hi>Neceſſaries</hi> to one another likewiſe.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, as any of theſe poor doe any thing more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in grace &amp; virtue and religion, ſo their friendſhip is more deſirable then otherwiſe, ſuch as theſe our Saviour here aimes at, the poor <hi>Saints</hi> as the Scripture terms them, Rom. 15.26. The godly and the faithful poor, which are the friends and favorites of Heaven, theſe he would have rich men to be ſure to make their friends above any other beſides, as being ſuch who will be friendly to them in the beſt things that are, and which make moſt for their advantage, as is alſo ſignified in the text, <hi>that they may receive ye into everlaſting habitations.</hi> From the Connexion of which words together <hi>Friends,</hi> and which <hi>will ſo receive you,</hi> the ſpirit of God does hint unto us who are indeed our trueſt friends and ſo to be accounted, namely ſuch as do further our <hi>Salvation</hi> are inſtruments of our <hi>Converſion,</hi> and are meanes and helps and occaſions of our coming to <hi>Heaven,</hi> theſe are the <hi>trueſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> friends of all; when ever we would make frinds <hi>indeed</hi> it will be our concernment to make <hi>ſuch.</hi> It is true, the world for the moſt part hath another eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and opinion of friendſhip, counting them the beſt friends, which are moſt <hi>oppoſite</hi> in theſe reſpects which flatter them, &amp; ſooth them, &amp; harden them and confirm them in wickedneſs, &amp; thoſe the greateſt <hi>Enemies,</hi> which deal moſt <hi>Freely</hi> &amp; plainly with them. <hi>Ionadab</hi> was <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non's</hi> friend, becauſe he promoted his <hi>Luſt:</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> was the <hi>Galatians</hi> Enemie becauſe he told them <hi>the truth</hi> but with <hi>God</hi> whoſe judgement is infallible, they of all others do beſt deſerve the name of <hi>Friends,</hi> who moſt concurre <hi>to the ſaving of the Soul.</hi> And that's
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30513:8"/>the firſt branch obſervable in this ſecond General, <hi>viz</hi> The <hi>thing</hi> adviſed to, <hi>the making of Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the <hi>meanes</hi> adviſed to whereby to effect it: And that is, By the <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſse,</hi> as it is here expreſt, by <hi>Mammon</hi> we are to underſtand <hi>Riches;</hi> concerning the <hi>Notation</hi> of which word there is ſome difference amongſt Interpreters, ſome would have it a <hi>Greek</hi> word, and ſo derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies to <hi>deſire earneſtly,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies <hi>Silver</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the ſame reaſon. But it ſeemes rather to be <hi>Syriach,</hi> and either fetcht from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies a <hi>Multitude</hi> or from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies to <hi>truſt,</hi> becauſe mens riches are commonly their <hi>confidence,</hi> and that thing wherein they place their chiefeſt relyance, <hi>The rich mans wealth is his ſtrong City, and as an high wall in his own conceit,</hi> Pro. 18.12. That for the <hi>notation</hi> of the word.</p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Mammon</hi> or <hi>Riches,</hi> it is here called the Mammon of <hi>iniquity,</hi> or of <hi>unrighteouſneſſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> whereby <hi>Chriſt</hi> would have thoſe who injoy it, to <hi>make themſelves friends,</hi> and here there are two things to be opened and explained by us. Firſt, the reaſon of the <hi>Denomination:</hi> why riches are here ſtyled the <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Secondly, <hi>the force of the Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> how this <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſse</hi> is ſo avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as to <hi>the making of friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, It is not ſo to be taken as a <hi>general and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal</hi> blot which is caſt upon <hi>all</hi> kind of riches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>exception:</hi> for <hi>riches</hi> are ſimply conſidered and in themſelves the <hi>good bleſsings</hi> of God, and ſo to be <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted;</hi> but they are called ſo from what they do prove moſt <hi>commonly</hi> and uſually in the <hi>event,</hi> through mans <hi>corruption,</hi> from whence it comes to paſs, that that which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30513:8"/>of its own <hi>Nature,</hi> and according to Gods <hi>inſtitution</hi> is the fruit and <hi>reward of induſtry,</hi> it becomes now by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary abuſe, and misimprovement, the very <hi>badge of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity,</hi> and accordingly hath the <hi>Name</hi> of Iniquity put upon it as it is here in the text, which agrees with another <hi>Notation</hi> which ſome give of the word, beſides that which we formerly mentioned, &amp; that is from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies a <hi>blot</hi> or fault which is uſually adherent thereunto, we may give an account of it in three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reference to the <hi>getting</hi> of it, it is the Mammon of <hi>unrightuouſneſse</hi> ſo as it is unrighteouſly <hi>purchaſed,</hi> for ſo it oftentimes is, <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.11. By fraud, and lying, and bribery, and extortion, and oppreſſion and the like, there are great eſtates in the world, which are got by ſuch meanes as theſe; yea indeed they are very few, which are got <hi>without</hi> them, or at leaſt without ſome kind of touch and tincture of them, hence is that ſaying of old which is Fathered upon St. <hi>Hierom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Omnis Dives eſt, aut Iniquus, aut Iniqui Haeres,</hi> That every rich man is either unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous himſelf or elſe is heir to ſome-body that was ſo before him. I will not take upon me to juſtify either the <hi>truth</hi> or the <hi>charity</hi> of that ſpeech, which ſeems to be very <hi>harſh</hi> and ſomewhat <hi>unreaſonable;</hi> but <hi>this</hi> I will be bold to ſay, that it is <hi>difficult</hi> (though not altogether <hi>impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>) very <hi>difficult</hi> it is out of queſtion, for a man to get a very <hi>great eſtate</hi> with a very <hi>clear and upright Conſcience,</hi> in regard of the manifold <hi>ſnares</hi> and temptations which attend thereupon.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, if we ſhall take it in its full <hi>latitude</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; as it concerns us to do; in reference not only to the <hi>meanes,</hi> but alſo to the <hi>time,</hi> which though it be ſeldome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30513:9"/>thought of, is very conſiderable in this particular; when men ſhall ſpend that time in the getting of <hi>wealth.</hi> Which they ſhould ſpend in the getting of <hi>grace.</hi> When they ſhall be following their trades in the <hi>world,</hi> when they ſhould be driving a trade for <hi>Heaven,</hi> when they ſhall be ſo ſunk, and immerſt, and ſwallowed up, in their ſecular imployments, as to have little or no leiſure for the duties and exerciſes of <hi>Piety,</hi> and religion, and the ſervice of God, intrench upon the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and that which is allotted to his worſhip. <hi>Amos.</hi> 8.5. So buſie at their <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> as they have no leiſure to look after their <hi>ſoules,</hi> or the ſoules of <hi>others</hi> that belong unto them: ſurely ſuch as theſe, though they may be free from couzenage <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,</hi> yet in a <hi>ſenſe</hi> they are guilty of it, and of that which is the worſt of all, which is the couzenage of <hi>themſelves.</hi> That wealth which is gotten <hi>unſeaſonably</hi> is gotten <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly,</hi> and the Mammon of <hi>Prophaneſs</hi> is no other then the Mammon of <hi>unrighteouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. In reference to the <hi>keeping</hi> of it, the Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe alſo from <hi>that</hi> as there are riches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly <hi>held</hi> and unjuſtly <hi>poſseſt:</hi> woe <hi>unto him that incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that which is not his: how long?</hi> and that <hi>ladeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with thick clay.</hi> Habb. 2.6. <hi>And the hire of the labourers, which is kept back by fraud crieth, and the cry of them is entered into the ears of the Lord of Sabbaoth.</hi> Iam. 5.4. <hi>Withold not good from them, who are the owners of it, when it is in the power of thine hand to give it.</hi> Pro. 3.27. <hi>An unrighteous injoymemt</hi> makes it to be the <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> that's the <hi>ſecond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. In reference to <hi>the uſe of it;</hi> hence it is alſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>unrighteous Mammon,</hi> becauſe it is ſo often <hi>improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> unrighteouſly, even to ſin and iniquity. <hi>Effodiuntur
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30513:9"/>opes irritamenta malorum,</hi> thoſe who have great <hi>eſtates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> they have from them great <hi>opportunites</hi> for the following and perſuing of their <hi>Luſts</hi> in all kinds; and they are not <hi>for</hi> the moſt part <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fective</hi> or wanting hereunto: but do improve them abundantly, to oppreſſion and luxury, and exceſs, and revenge, and uncleanneſs, and all kind of wickedneſſe. It was that which the holy man <hi>Agur,</hi> was ſo jealous and ſuſpicious of <hi>himſelf</hi> for <hi>in reference to riches,</hi> leaſt he <hi>ſhould be full and deny God,</hi> and ſay who is the <hi>Lord?</hi> becauſe he knew that ſuch <hi>corruptions</hi> did very frequently attend ſuch <hi>conditions.</hi> Thus we ſee how in all theſe reſpects this <hi>denomination</hi> is very ſutable; the <hi>Mammon of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this expreſſion it is not lightly to be paſſed over by us, but is improveable to very good purpoſe. Firſt, to <hi>humble</hi> us, in the conſideration of our <hi>ſinful nature</hi> which does thus taint and pollute ſuch things as theſe are to us. <hi>Riches,</hi> (as I ſaid before) they are of themſelves the <hi>gifts of God,</hi> &amp; they are <hi>bleſsings</hi> rather than any thing elſe: they are ſuch as God does beſtow upon men, as rewards of <hi>virtue</hi> and goodneſs in them; therefore we may not abſolutely &amp; indefinitely ſpeake againſt them, or againſt thoſe which enjoy them: it is an <hi>envious</hi> humour in many people, that becauſe they want riches <hi>themſelves,</hi> to reproach them in others, as they do alſo now and then ſome <hi>other</hi> quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications beſides: we know that diverſe, <hi>Godly</hi> perſons have bin poſſeſſours of great eſtates; as <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> and the reſt. Wealth hath no <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenſecal</hi> evil or vitiouſneſſe in it. But that evil which it hath, it hath from the <hi>ſin</hi> of man, which intermingling it ſelf with it, does denominate it the <hi>Mammon of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30513:10"/>
            <p>Indeed there is nothing at all which we have to do with, but according as we may uſe it, it may prove to be <hi>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity</hi> to us, and may very well have the <hi>title</hi> of iniquity faſtened upon it: It is the <hi>Honour</hi> of iniquity when it is uſed to <hi>Pride,</hi> and inſultation: it is the <hi>power</hi> of iniquity when it is uſed to <hi>violence</hi> and oppreſſion; It is the <hi>beauty</hi> of iniquity, when it is uſed to <hi>wantonneſse</hi> and laſcivious allurements: nay further, it is the <hi>wit and learning</hi> of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, when it is uſed to the promoting of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and the conveying of erroneus opinions. And ſo here now the <hi>Mammon</hi> of iniquity, when it is unrighteouſly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, poſſeſſed and improved and yet this no way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the <hi>things</hi> themſelves which are injoy'd, but upon the <hi>Perſons</hi> of thoſe that enjoy them. <hi>To the pure all things are pure, but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving, is nothing pure; but even their minde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is defiled.</hi> Tit. 1.15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It ſhould very much divert us from an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate love</hi> of theſe things, and turne as it were our ſtomachs againſt them, which have ſuch diſparagements put upon them, which the ſpirit of God does on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe chooſe to do, thereby to <hi>alienate</hi> our affections from them: As nurſes do commonly with their children, when they would keep them from any thing which may be hurtful, they put dreadful names upon it: ſo does the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt</hi> with <hi>us,</hi> both here and in other places. The better any <hi>creature</hi> is in its own Nature, which is of worldly and earthly conſideration, the more does the Scripture uſually diſparage it, that ſo it may teach us not to truſt, or to rely upon it, but it does it in nothing more then in <hi>riches,</hi> and worldly wealth, for this very reaſon whereof we now ſpeak, which ſhould therefore prevail with us.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30513:10"/>
            <p>Thirdly, It ſhould ſtir us up to the greater care and caution and circumſpection, ſeeing it is the Mammon of <hi>Iniquity</hi> moſt frequently and uſually, and for the greateſt part. Oh what need have we then to be very wary and heedfull about it! what need have thoſe which are rich to be very watchful over their own hearts in all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that ſo they may not be defiled with the <hi>iniquity</hi> of them? what though it be not ſo alwaies, (as I have ſhown that indeed it is not) yet if it be <hi>often,</hi> that's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and ſuch as may very much awaken men to look to themſelves, becauſe as the Philoſopher tells us. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That which is often is next to that which is alwaies.</hi> We know how in other matters we are ſhie, not only of <hi>certainties,</hi> but alſo of <hi>probabilities</hi> of danger: not only of theſe evils which <hi>will</hi> be, and which we are ſure cannot be avoided: but alſo of thoſe evils which <hi>may</hi> be, and which are poſſible at leaſt to come to paſſe, and how much more does it concern us then to be ſo in the caſe of our ſoules, which are uſually in ſo much hazzard and danger from theſe occaſions, though ſometimes through Gods goodneſs they eſcape it. The Apoſtle hath ſufficiently declared it and given teſtimony of it. 1 Tim. 6.9. <hi>But they that will be rich, fall into temptation and a ſnare, and into many foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition.</hi> How feareful are men of ſuch paſſages, where they are in danger of <hi>drowning!</hi> ſuch is this which we have here in this text of a <hi>great eſtate,</hi> and yet not ſo much from the <hi>Eſtate</hi> neither as from the minde. It is not they that <hi>are</hi> rich, but they that <hi>will</hi> be ſo: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> who are ſet and <hi>reſolved</hi> to be ſo <hi>per fas aut nefas,</hi> either by hook or crook. Theſe are the Men which are indeed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30513:11"/>in ſuch danger: and what cauſe is there then (I ſay) for great watchfulneſs and vigilancie in ſuch conditions! That which is one mans <hi>ruine,</hi> it ſhould be another mans <hi>caution.</hi> Certainly thoſe men which have <hi>great eſtates</hi> in their <hi>hands,</hi> they had need to have great <hi>grace</hi> in their <hi>hearts,</hi> to prevent them and to preſerve them from the <hi>temptations</hi> of thoſe eſtates. They had need to keep in <hi>good termes</hi> with God, and to be much in <hi>communion</hi> with him, <hi>that ſo pleaſing him, they may not be taken in ſuch ſnares.</hi> Eccles. 7, 26. <hi>Magnaefelicitatis est à fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitate non vinci,</hi> ſayes, <hi>Aug.</hi> It is a great <hi>happineſſe</hi> not to be <hi>overcome</hi> by happineſs. And when <hi>riches increaſe not to ſet our hearts upon them</hi> as <hi>David</hi> adviſes <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62, 10. The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a ſaying amongſt them, <hi>That a man that hath riches, had need to ſeaſon and powder his riches,</hi> and accordingly they add this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, <hi>the ſalt of riches is righteouſneſse, or the ſalt of riches is kindneſſe</hi> and liberality, and bounty to the poor, which will preſerve it and keep it it from noiſomeneſs and putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and ſo much of the firſt inquiry, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>reaſon of the denomination,</hi> why riches are here ſtyled by our bleſſed Saviour the riches of <hi>iniquity</hi> or the Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the <hi>force of the improvement,</hi> how this <hi>Mammon of unrighteouſneſse</hi> proves ſo availeable &amp; effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious to the <hi>making of friends,</hi> or is required ſo to doe as is here implyed? where, before we go any further, we muſt remove a <hi>difficulty</hi> and objection which lyes in our way, it may ſeem by what is here expreſt, as if our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in ſome ſort did approve of riches unlawfully got, or unlawfully poſſeſt: becauſe without any further taxation, or cenſure upon them, but only naming them, he does adviſe the perſons he ſpeaks to, that they would <hi>make
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30513:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelves friends of them,</hi> and ſo thereby as it were make ſome <hi>recompence</hi> for the <hi>iniquity</hi> of them, which is indeed the beſt uſe and improvement which too many make of this <hi>counſel:</hi> but this was <hi>farr</hi> enough from the minde of our bleſſed Saviour, who whiles he call'd it the <hi>Mammon of iniquity,</hi> does not thereby ſo much ſignify what it <hi>may</hi> be, as what it uſually <hi>is</hi> through mens <hi>abuſe,</hi> and his meaning is no more but this, that wealth which <hi>others</hi> for the moſt part doe improve as an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>iniquity,</hi> do <hi>yee</hi> improve to the good <hi>of your ſoules,</hi> as the furtherance of your eternal ſalvation; by making to your ſelves ſuch friends as may be uſeful, and helpful to you in that particular.</p>
            <p>Now this (that we may know how it is done) is briefly by <hi>expending</hi> and laying out of thoſe riches upon them, whiles rich men doe contribute of their eſtates, to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and ſupply of poor Chiſtians, they do thereby get ſo many friends, which may further them in their way to Heaven, where there are two things intimated to us. Firſt, heres the <hi>duty and diſpoſition</hi> of thoſe which are <hi>poor:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly here is the <hi>priviledge and concernment</hi> of thoſe which are <hi>rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, here's the <hi>poor</hi> man's <hi>duty</hi> and (if he be right) his <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> which is, being <hi>relieved</hi> by the <hi>rich,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>friend</hi> unto him. This our Saviour here plainly ſuppoſes and takes for granted, whiles he ſpeaks to rich men to make the poor to be their friends by the relieving of them, he ſuppoſed that being ſo relieved they will be indeed friends unto them: and ſo they <hi>will:</hi> and ſo they <hi>ought:</hi> It is that which is <hi>expected</hi> from them. Indeed oftentimes through mens <hi>corruption,</hi> it proves otherwiſe in the <hi>event,</hi> it is the baſe <hi>ingratitude</hi> and unworthyneſſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30513:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of ſome kind of people to be leaſt of all friends there, where they have received the greateſt friendſhip: thoſe who have done them the greateſt kindneſſes, beſtowed the moſt coſt upon them, bin moſt charitable and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful towards them, thoſe are the perſons oftentimes who are moſt hated and maligned by them, and they are the deadlieſt Enemies againſt them, ſo fearful a Creature is a man when he once degenerates. But this is <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uous</hi> and unnatural, and contrary to all <hi>rational ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation;</hi> it is that which one would not <hi>look for,</hi> and therefore does our Saviour in this place ſuppoſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, he makes account that theſe rich men, whiles they are free of their Riches to the poor they will thereby make them their friends.</p>
            <p>And indeed ſo they <hi>will:</hi> where ever they are that which they <hi>ſhould</hi> be, where they are <hi>godly, and Chriſtian</hi> poor, they will be ready to make <hi>conſcience</hi> of ſuch grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful returnes as theſe are. <hi>Piety</hi> its full of its <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> and ther's a great deal of <hi>good-Nature</hi> in <hi>grace,</hi> from whence it thinks it can never doe enough for thoſe perſons by whom it is befriended, but is therefore <hi>careful</hi> and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to make all acknowledgement that poſſibly may be. A godly man that hath received a kindneſſe from any one, he labours to <hi>requite</hi> that kindneſs in the beſt way that he may, and where he cannot do it in <hi>kind,</hi> yet at leaſt to doe it in <hi>aequivolence:</hi> or rather in <hi>tranſcendence,</hi> he thinks it a very equal thing, that thoſe who have ſowen <hi>Carnals</hi> ſhould reap <hi>ſpirituals,</hi> which therefore he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours as he is able to repay them withall, this is the poore Chriſtians both <hi>Duty</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Diſpoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Here is alſo the rich mans <hi>Priviledge and concernment,</hi> that he may have friends by ſuch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30513:12"/>meanes as theſe. This is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> calls it: The <hi>moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious way to Salvation, and the eaſieſt aſcent to Heaven,</hi> not that this does exclude their own <hi>indeavour</hi> as to the <hi>wayes of piety;</hi> which are to be taken in with the other, as we ſhall heare more anon. Indeed there are ſome now and then who are ready to exclude it, and to reſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the intereſt which they have either in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or affection of thoſe which are better then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: think if they be acquainted with ſuch and ſuch holy Chriſtians or godly Miniſters, and be a little encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged by them in that which is good, that this is enough for them, &amp; that they need not to look any further, but this is an uncertain prop, &amp; ſo will prove at another day. No rather as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> adviſes, let every man <hi>prove his own work that ſo he may have rejoycing in himſelf alone, &amp; not in another</hi> Gal. 6.4. The beſt men may be miſtaken in their apprehenſions of ſuch and ſuch perſons, and oftentimes are; but yet it is an advantage to have their affections to this end which we now ſpeak of, &amp; ſo to be improved: &amp; it is the ſubſtance of our Saviours council and advice here in the text, he would have them to make uſe of their wealth to ſuch a purpoſe as this is, as which would be moſt profitable to them; we ſee how it is with men in other matters as to the things of the world, they would make friends of their riches <hi>here</hi> all they can; for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing of their <hi>liberty;</hi> for the recovery of their <hi>health,</hi> for the aſſuring of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> for the promoting of their <hi>requeſts:</hi> their riches make <hi>room</hi> for them, as <hi>Solomon</hi> tell's us, <hi>brings them before great men.</hi> Prov. 18.16. Men make themſelves friends of their wealth in the Courts of <hi>Earth,</hi> and how much more does it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30513:13"/>them to doe ſo in the Court of <hi>Heaven:</hi> eſpecially conſidering that there is no other way to do it ſo expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as this. They that know not how to faſten any thing upon the <hi>Maſter,</hi> they deal with his <hi>ſervants,</hi> and this is the caſe <hi>here.</hi> As for <hi>God himſelf</hi> our riches are no way pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to <hi>him,</hi> nor cannot advantage him: now therefore beſtow them upon thoſe which are <hi>his,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it. Pſal. 16.2. <hi>My goodneſse extendeth not unto thee O God, but unto the Saints which are on earth, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the excellent, in whom is my delight.</hi> Men love in a way of the <hi>world</hi> to make as <hi>many friends</hi> as they can of that which they have: let them learn to do ſo in theſe <hi>ſpiritual Improvements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whiles it is ſaid here in the text, <hi>Make to your ſelves friends,</hi> there ſeemes to be a ſpecial emphaſis in every word, which accordingly is conſiderable of us.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In the word <hi>friends,</hi> theres a ſpecial importance in <hi>that,</hi> namely; to guide and direct them in the <hi>manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and ordering of their liberality, that they doe it with the beſt prudence and diſcretion that may be, as to the <hi>quality</hi> &amp; diſpoſition of the Perſons, upon whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it: not only that they be ſuch as are ſimply and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or</hi> in regard of their <hi>neceſsities:</hi> but alſo that they be ſuch as are likely conſcionably to improve it in regard of their <hi>deſerts,</hi> otherwiſe it is not <hi>beſtowed</hi> but <hi>caſt away.</hi> To <hi>make friends</hi> of an eſtate is ſo to diſpoſe it, as that thoſe who doe partake of it, may indeed become <hi>friends from</hi> it: they are not likely to receive <hi>others</hi> into <hi>everlaſting Habitations,</hi> which have no intereſt in them <hi>themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. For the word <hi>make,</hi> theres ſome force alſo (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) in <hi>that,</hi> to teach men not only to ſhew mercy to their neareſt relations and ſuch as are friends already<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30513:13"/>from the bonds of <hi>Nature</hi> or otherwiſe: but likewiſe ſomtimes to thoſe which are <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> &amp; at the greateſt diſtance and remoteneſſe: it is not <hi>take</hi> friends onely but <hi>make</hi> them, and <hi>begin</hi> as it were with them. That's a good beginning of friendſhip, which has its foundation layd in <hi>Beneficence</hi> and the contributions of Charity.</p>
            <p n="3">III. In the word <hi>to your ſilves,</hi> ther's ſomewhat likewiſe in <hi>that,</hi> which is to ſhew that by acts of bounty and liberality done to the poor, men, are not ſo much friends to <hi>others,</hi> as rather in concluſion to <hi>themſelves:</hi> and provide for their <hi>own accommodation;</hi> and ſo I have done alſo with the ſecond general part of the text, which is the Council here of our Saviour to rich men, <hi>make to your ſelves friends of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt is the argument or ground for the practiſe of it. <hi>That when ye fail they may receive you into everlaſting Habitations.</hi> In which laſt paſſage of the text, there are two branches further conſiderable, Firſt the deſignation of the <hi>time,</hi> Secondly, the ſpecificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>benefit:</hi> the deſignation of the <hi>time,</hi> that we have in thoſe words, <hi>that when ye fail.</hi> The ſpecifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>benefit</hi> that we have in theſe <hi>they may receive you into everlaſting habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, of the <hi>deſignation of the time, when ye fail,</hi> that is in one word when <hi>ye dye,</hi> where again are two things which we ſhall take notice off, 1. Of the <hi>Phraſe</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. 2. Of the <hi>thing it ſelf, or notion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Phraſe</hi> or expresſion, firſt, we ſee here how <hi>Death</hi> is exhibited, and repreſented unto us, and that is as a <hi>Fayling,</hi> and defection: and ſo indeed it is as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this preſent world; a fayling of ſtrength, of parts, of Senſes, of underſtanding &amp;c. All failes in death, yea
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30513:14"/>that which <hi>rich</hi> men have in their lives moſt made of, it muſt then faile unto them, this <hi>mammon of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſse,</hi> which is here mentioned in the text, <hi>that</hi> muſt faile too amongſt the reſt: and accordingly ſome Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as namely the <hi>Syriac</hi> and <hi>Ethiopick</hi> doe tranſlate the words <hi>when IT failes,</hi> meaning the <hi>Mammon,</hi> and ſo in like manner our <hi>old Engliſh tranſlators,</hi> that when ye ſhall <hi>want,</hi> namely that wealth, and ſubſtance and riches which now ye injoy, for there is a time for the <hi>deficiency</hi> of it, when it will <hi>ceaſe</hi> unto you. As for <hi>rich</hi> men to <hi>faile,</hi> this ſeems to be very <hi>inconſonant</hi> and in conſiſtent, it is almoſt <hi>contradictio in adjecto.</hi> Ther's none, who are <hi>leſs</hi> in danger of failing in the ſenſe of the <hi>world</hi> than thoſe that are <hi>rich,</hi> yea but yet even <hi>theſe</hi> may alſo faile in the ſenſe of the <hi>text,</hi> they may faile <hi>to</hi> the world when they do not faile <hi>in</hi> it, and that is when they faile <hi>from</hi> it, and leave and forſake it, when their <hi>life</hi> once <hi>failes</hi> them, every thing elſe alſo failes which is pertinent to it, and ſo their <hi>riches</hi> amongſt the reſt.</p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of this paſſage, it may not be amiſs for us to reflect upon the word in the <hi>Original.</hi> The <hi>greek</hi> word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies <hi>Eclipſin pati,</hi> to be under an <hi>Eclipſe:</hi> and indeed <hi>Death</hi> is ſuch a thing as that is in <hi>either</hi> reſpects, whether we take it in the ſenſe of <hi>Aggravation</hi> as an evil enlarged, or whether we take it in the ſenſe of <hi>extenuation,</hi> as an evil <hi>diminiſhed,</hi> in either of theſe ſences it is an <hi>Ecclipſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, take it in the ſenſe of <hi>diſparagement</hi> and aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and it is an Ecclipſe, <hi>ſo</hi> as it is a failing of <hi>Light</hi> to thoſe who are under the power of it, therefore we do ſo often read of the <hi>darkneſs of death,</hi> becauſe the eyes are therein deprived of that light which now they injoy, It is a deprivation of <hi>Natural light,</hi> as it is an ecclipſe of thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30513:14"/>
               <hi>Natural comforts,</hi> which are pertinent to the life of Man. And it is a deprivation of <hi>wordly light,</hi> as it is an Eclipſe of thoſe <hi>ſecular</hi> comforts; whereby our <hi>natural</hi> life is made more <hi>ſweet</hi> and comfortable unto us, yea it is alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times according to the <hi>circumſtances</hi> of it a deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>ſpiritual light,</hi> likewiſe in the Eclipſe of the light of <hi>Gods countenance</hi> ſhining upon the ſoul; which now and then at ſuch times eſpecially is obſcured and darkened through the black interpoſitions of <hi>Satan,</hi> who is the <hi>ſpiritual enemie,</hi> in theſe and the like conſiderations, may it juſtly have the name of an <hi>Eclipſe</hi> put upon it, in its ſenſe of <hi>aggravation,</hi> as being ſo much.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, it is an eclipſe alſo in its ſenſe of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation</hi> as being <hi>no more.</hi> We know that in an <hi>Eclipſe</hi> though the <hi>Sunn and Moon</hi> be darkned <hi>for a time,</hi> yet they are not darkned <hi>perpetually,</hi> but doe <hi>recover</hi> their light again to themſelves, and with the greater advantage; even ſo it is alſo in <hi>death:</hi> though there be a failing of light and life for a <hi>time,</hi> yet there is a <hi>recovery,</hi> and returne again of them, theres a failing of them in <hi>Death,</hi> but there is a recovery of them again in <hi>Reſurrestion,</hi> when Death ſhall be ſwallowed up into <hi>victory</hi> and perfect abolition, as the <hi>Church</hi> expreſſes it concerning her own conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Mic. 7.8. Though <hi>I fall,</hi> yet I ſhall <hi>riſe</hi> again, though I ſit in <hi>darkneſſe</hi> yet the Lord ſhall be a <hi>light</hi> unto me. And thus much may be ſpoken of the <hi>Phraſe</hi> or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, which is here uſed of <hi>dying,</hi> when as it is called a <hi>Failing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now further for the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf and <hi>notion,</hi> we may here take notice how <hi>ſeaſonably</hi> our bleſſed Saviour does put <hi>rich</hi> men in minde of <hi>Death,</hi> and ſuggeſt to them thoughts and meditations of their <hi>latter end:</hi> when ye
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30513:15"/>
               <hi>faile,</hi> that is (as we have explained it) when ye <hi>dye,</hi> as conſidering that that was a time which they muſt one day <hi>come to:</hi> and therefore was fitting for them to <hi>think</hi> of, and ſo to hear of. The thoughts and meditations of Death as they become all men beſides, ſo are they eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially proper and pertinent to men of great and <hi>large Eſtates,</hi> and they had need to be put <hi>in minde</hi> of them, whiles our Saviour mentions the one, he mentions the <hi>other</hi> with it, whiles he ſpeaks of <hi>Mammon,</hi> he ſpeaks alſo of <hi>fayling.</hi> This is eſpecially requiſite upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count;</p>
            <p n="1">I. To <hi>moderate their affections</hi> in the purſuit and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of them that they may not be too earneſt and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in following after them: but there may be an <hi>end</hi> of their deſires in this particular, and they may ſay, <hi>there is enough</hi> whiles the <hi>Iourney</hi> is but <hi>ſhort,</hi> why ſhould the proviſion be long?</p>
            <p n="2">II. To <hi>abate their pride</hi> and to prevent them from too much <hi>confidence</hi> and relyance on ſuch things as theſe are, <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high minded</hi> ſayes the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> 1 Tim. 6, 17. <hi>Nor truſt in uncertain riches,</hi> whereby he would ſignify both that rich men are apt to be <hi>high minded;</hi> as alſo that a good <hi>meanes</hi> to keep them and prevent them from it, is by perſwading them of the <hi>uncertainty</hi> of their riches, and the <hi>uncerntainty</hi> of them does much lye in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of <hi>life,</hi> ſeeing <hi>that</hi> within a while ſhall faile, and ſo their <hi>wealth</hi> with it, what cauſe have they then to be <hi>ſwollen</hi> and lifted up in themſelves for it, as ſometimes they prove to be? theres no ſuch check upon <hi>pride</hi> as <hi>death,</hi> which <hi>levels</hi> all men both <hi>poor and rich,</hi> and makes them indeed to <hi>meet together. Duſt thou art</hi> (O proud
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30513:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>man) <hi>and to duſt thou ſhalt return,</hi> ye <hi>ſhall dye like men and fall like one of the Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. To provoke them to a wiſe <hi>ordering and diſpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of their <hi>eſtates,</hi> they muſt one day <hi>dye:</hi> therefore let them doe good whiles they <hi>live,</hi> their eſtates muſt in time be <hi>left,</hi> becauſe their <hi>lives</hi> muſt be taken away from them, therefore let them <hi>diſpoſe</hi> their eſtates whiles they live to the beſt advantage: whats the reaſon that many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have had their eſtates ſquandered and imbezzel'd and come to nothing after their <hi>deaths?</hi> It hath bin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that whiles they <hi>lived</hi> they did not ſo ſeriouſly think they ſhould <hi>dye</hi> as that which might have excited them to have taken better care about them, that they might be improved, when as themſelves ſhould be gone.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſuch perſons as thoſe ſhould <hi>ſuffer the words of exhortation,</hi> It is that which becomes thoſe which are <hi>Miniſters</hi> to uſe unto them as our <hi>Saviour</hi> does here in the text, and it is ſuch as becomes thoſe which are <hi>rich</hi> to receive from them with all <hi>patience</hi> and meekneſs of <hi>Spirit,</hi> and not to <hi>put away farr off from them the evil day;</hi> as <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh of <hi>France</hi> who lying ſick, upon great penalty forbade the <hi>mentioning</hi> of <hi>death</hi> within his Court. And ſo much of the firſt branch obſervable in this third general, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>deſignation of the time; when ye faile,</hi> that is <hi>when ye dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the <hi>ſpecification of the benefit,</hi> in theſe words <hi>that they may receive you into everlaſting Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> where the argument is taken from the <hi>End</hi> or <hi>Conſequent</hi> of the fore-mentioned practiſe, it is both <hi>ut Intentionaliter,</hi> and alſo <hi>ut Conſecutivè,</hi> and it implyes three things in it.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:30513:16"/>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>deſign</hi> on the part of thoſe that are <hi>rich,</hi> which they are to <hi>aime</hi> at, and that is <hi>to go into everlasting Habitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly; the <hi>practiſe</hi> on the part of thoſe which are <hi>poor</hi> which they will <hi>performe,</hi> and that is to <hi>bring</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> thoſe rich perſons <hi>thereinto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>iſſue</hi> or effect in regard of the thing it ſelf, and that is that they ſhall indeed be <hi>received</hi> and brought into them.</p>
            <p>Firſt here is implyed the <hi>deſign</hi> on the part of thoſe that are <hi>rich,</hi> which they are to <hi>aime</hi> at, &amp; to propound to themſelves: and that is that when they <hi>go hence,</hi> they may <hi>go into everlaſting habitations,</hi> that when they dye they may goe to <hi>Heaven,</hi> this is that which they are to have in their eye: and this is the meaning of this expreſſion wherein again there are three things yet further imply'd.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that there are <hi>everlaſting Habitations</hi> which are reſerved for the people of God in another world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that theſe <hi>everlaſting Habitations</hi> they are entred upon immediately upon <hi>Death</hi> and diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that it is <hi>all</hi> mens concernment, and of <hi>rich</hi> men more eſpecially to take care that when they <hi>faile,</hi> that is <hi>dye,</hi> they may have entrance and admiſſion <hi>herein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> may be <hi>received into theſe everlaſting Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, there <hi>are everlaſting Habitations,</hi> which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd for the people of God in another world. 2 Cor. 5.1. <hi>We know</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolv'd, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the heavens.</hi> The word <hi>tabernacle,</hi> it is of it ſelf a word of ſhort cotinuance but if you add <hi>everlaſting</hi> to it (as it is here in the text)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30513:16"/>then it becomes a word of <hi>perpetuity,</hi> and ſo indeed it is: It is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as we finde that expreſſion uſed concerning <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> Eſay. 33.20. <hi>A taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle that ſhall not be taken down, nor one of the ſtakes thereof removed, neither any of the Cords there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ever be broken.</hi> In my <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> (ſayes Chriſt) are many <hi>manſions,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Continued</hi> Habitations <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.2,</p>
            <p>Alas, for theſe <hi>Cottages</hi> and Habitations here below, which we many times make ſo much off, and keep ſuch a ſtirr to hold, &amp; enjoy and to poſſeſs our ſelves of them, though mens inward thoughts is that <hi>theſe houſes ſhall continue for ever, &amp; their dwelling places to all generations.</hi> Pſal. 49.11. Yet what <hi>fading</hi> things are they in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Houſes of <hi>Clay,</hi> Tabernacles of the <hi>Duſt,</hi> Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which will quickly <hi>moulder</hi> and vaniſh away; weare <hi>here</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> having no certain dwelling place, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks 1 Cor. 4.11. Oh but thoſe <hi>dwellings</hi> which God has provided for his people in another world, they are ſuch as are dwellings <hi>indeed,</hi> where the <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> is ſure of the dwelling: and the dwelling is ſure <hi>to</hi> the Inhabitant, they are <hi>everlaſting habitations</hi> as it is here expreſt unto us, that's the <hi>firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, theſe everlaſting Habitations they are entred upon immediately upon <hi>Death,</hi> this we gather from the <hi>cloſe conjunction</hi> of theſe two both together in the text, that <hi>when</hi> ye faile they may <hi>receive you,</hi> that is, that they may receive you <hi>upon</hi> your fayling. The ſoules of the faithful goe to Heaven preſently upon their departure out of this world, as ſoon as ever they are <hi>ſet looſe</hi> they are with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> aſſoon as they are abſent from the <hi>body</hi> they are preſent with the <hi>Lord,</hi> when this <hi>earthly Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:30513:17"/>is taken down, they have a <hi>building of God</hi> not made with hands, when they <hi>faile,</hi> they do out of hand paſs to theſe <hi>everlaſting Habitations,</hi> that ſo there may be no room left for <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or <hi>Limbus,</hi> and ſuch fopperies as theſe are.</p>
            <p>And then again, <hi>when</hi> ye faile, that is, as we may take it <hi>excluſively</hi> not <hi>till then,</hi> theres no paſſage (ordinarily) to Heaven but by <hi>Death,</hi> that's the <hi>Iron gate</hi> that leades to the <hi>City of Gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, which is the main thing here conſiderable, it is the great concernment of <hi>all men,</hi> and eſpecially of thoſe that are <hi>rich</hi> to take care, that when they dye they may be received into thoſe everlaſting Habitations: this is that which our Saviour does cheiflly offer and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound here unto them: and accordingly we ſhould be ſenſible of it, and affected with it, and endeavour after it, that when we muſt at laſt part with all theſe things here below, yet we may have ſomewhat elſe to hold to, which ſhall not be parted withal nor taken away from us, that when this earthly <hi>Tabernacle ſhall be diſsolved</hi> we may have (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of himſelf in the place before cited) <hi>an Houſe in the Heavens.</hi> We ſee how it is the Nature of every man, as to the affairs of this preſent life when he thinks he ſhall be turned out of <hi>one</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to provide himſelf what he can of <hi>another:</hi> no man would willingly ly in the ſtreets, but have a place whereto he might <hi>retire</hi> for his habitation, and why ſhould we not then be as wiſe and provident, as to our <hi>ſpiritual and eternal</hi> condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved,</hi> the world will one day turne us all out of doors, and whither <hi>then?</hi> and whither then? <hi>Quae tunc abibis in loca?</hi> Oh it will be a miſerable thing with that <hi>Emperour Adrian</hi> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:30513:17"/>know <hi>whether:</hi> to be deſtitute and to have no where to goe, at leaſt where we may have any comfort or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment for our <hi>abode and continuance.</hi> Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be perſwaded to lay hold on the preſent opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which God in providence affords unto us, <hi>let us lay up in ſtore to ourſelves a good foundation againſt the time to come,</hi> laying hold on <hi>eternal life.</hi> As St. <hi>Paul</hi> does in particular adviſe <hi>rich</hi> men to do; in that excellent ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18. Let us take time, whiles time ſerves: whiles the day <hi>of life and grace</hi> is continued ſtill unto us. The time for providing for <hi>Heaven</hi> is whiles we remain here upon <hi>earth:</hi> we know how it is in other matters, men do, not ſtay till they are out of their <hi>old</hi> houſe before they get them a <hi>new</hi> one, but get a new one at leaſt in ſome readineſe &amp; preparation before the old one be gone, whiles they <hi>ſtay</hi> &amp; continue ſtill in it, and ſo let ourſelves learn to do, as to our fittings and preparations for <hi>Heaven</hi> &amp; another world; let us do it whiles we abode in <hi>this,</hi> for it will be too late to doe it afterwards, when theſe dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſhall be taken away from us. Therefore it is worth our obſervation, that is in effect here ſaid in the text, make your ſelves friends <hi>now</hi> that when ye faile, they may not faile you <hi>then.</hi> In the Greek it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Aoriſt: have</hi> made your ſelves friends already. <hi>Be afore-hand</hi> in this particuler, doe good <hi>now,</hi> that ye may reap the <hi>fruit</hi> of it <hi>hereafter.</hi> There are many who never think of doing good till juſt the time when they ſhould have the <hi>benefit</hi> of it: never think of <hi>ſowing</hi> till then when it is time to <hi>reap:</hi> therefore if they make themſelves <hi>friends</hi> of their <hi>riches</hi> it is perhaps only juſt when they <hi>dye</hi> and are <hi>going,</hi> or are rather already <hi>gone</hi> out of the world, But alas I ther's <hi>then</hi> no opportunity for thoſe friends whom
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30513:18"/>they have made to doe this <hi>office</hi> of friends unto them. If ever it be done at all, it muſt be done before. Whiles God gives us time upon <hi>earth,</hi> we ſhould be plotting, and contriving for <hi>Heaven,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this is the concernment of <hi>all</hi> men, (ſo to ſpeak more cloſely to the text) it is of <hi>rich</hi> men more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially above the reſt. Ther's none have more need to make ſure of <hi>Heaven,</hi> then thoſe who have <hi>most</hi> of <hi>earth.</hi> And that upon a two-fold conſideration. The one is the <hi>difficulty</hi> of <hi>obtaining.</hi> And the other is the <hi>ſadneſse</hi> of <hi>miſcarrying,</hi> which is a great deal more in them than in any other.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the difficulty of <hi>obtaining.</hi> Our Saviour hath given notice of it, that it is <hi>hard</hi> for a rich man to <hi>enter into the Kingdome of God:</hi> and in deed ſo it is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thoſe manifold <hi>blocks</hi> and inpediments, which ly in his way: which we ſpake of before. This if it doth not take off our minds from <hi>looking after</hi> riches, as it ſeldome does; yet at leaſt it ſhould <hi>ſtirr up</hi> our mindes to be more watchful over ourſelves in them: and more active in the <hi>purſuits</hi> of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, from the <hi>ſadneſse of the miſcarriage,</hi> the <hi>better</hi> that men have lived <hi>in this</hi> world the more <hi>tedious</hi> will it be to them to be diſappointed of happineſſe in <hi>another. Felix miſer maximè miſer.</hi> Thoſe who are miſerable in the loſs and deprivation of former happineſs are the moſt miſerable of all: and ſo it is here, to go out of a <hi>Pallace</hi> into a <hi>Priſon,</hi> yea into a <hi>Dungeon,</hi> and pit of <hi>deſtruction,</hi> what a <hi>lamentable</hi> caſe is this! when men ſhall have lived here in the world in all kind of <hi>jollity and delight,</hi> and had what ever <hi>their hearts could wiſh,</hi> and then at laſt be turned into <hi>Hell,</hi> into that <hi>lake</hi> which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30513:18"/>burnes with <hi>fire and brimſtone</hi> for ever; where there is weeping and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth, where the worme never dyes and the fire never goes out! To have had <hi>no changes before</hi> in all their life: and now to meet with ſuch a change as this; Oh it will be a <hi>change indeed.</hi> What is the hope of the <hi>Hypocrite, though he hath gain'd, when God taketh away his ſoul,</hi> Iob. 27.8. Thou fool: this <hi>night thy ſoul ſhall be taken from thee; and then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be, which thou haſt provided.</hi> Luk. 12.20. Thus it is when men are rich to the <hi>world</hi> but are not rich to <hi>God.</hi> The caſe is ſtrangely alter'd with them, over what it was <hi>here. When the wicked ſpring as the graſſe and the workers of Iniquity flouriſh</hi> it is that they may be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>ever</hi> Pſal. 92.7.</p>
            <p>Therefore let all rich perſons eſpecially be <hi>awakened</hi> in this particular, yea let all of us together be perſwaded to minde thoſe things which <hi>concern our peace,</hi> that when we leave theſe <hi>earthly tabernables,</hi> we may be received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe <hi>everlaſting Habitations.</hi> That when we go to <hi>our long home,</hi> we may go to <hi>our eternal houſe,</hi> which we ſhall be poſſeſt of for ever. We ſee in the world when men remove and go to houſe, they love if they can to ſettle and not to change, to have ſuch habitations as they may deſire never to leave: becauſe removeals are troubleſome, &amp; why ſhould we not deſire the ſame alſo as to our ſettlements for Heaven? that when we <hi>faile</hi> we may <hi>not</hi> faile, <hi>when our fleſh and our heart</hi> failes us, yet <hi>God may be the ſtrength of our hearts and our portion for ever.</hi> Pſal. 73.26. That though we faile as to <hi>Nature;</hi> yet we may not faile as to <hi>Grace,</hi> and ſo conſequently not faile of <hi>Glory: Turpe eſt in extremo deficere.</hi> It is counted a <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable</hi> buſineſs to faile at the <hi>last,</hi> let us as much as we are able prevent this diſhonour to our ſelves with the ſad
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30513:19"/>conſequents of it, and the miſeries which are attendant upon it, for they that go not into the <hi>everlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> they ſhall goe into the <hi>everlaſting burnings.</hi> And thats the firſt particular obſerveable in this laſt paſſage, namely, the <hi>deſign</hi> on the part of thoſe who are <hi>rich,</hi> and which they are to aime at; and that is that <hi>when they dye they may go into everlaſting Habitations,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the <hi>practiſe</hi> on the part of thoſe that are <hi>poor,</hi> which they will <hi>performe,</hi> and that is to <hi>bring, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> thoſe <hi>rich</hi> perſons, who have bin friendly to them into theſe places, that they may <hi>receive you &amp;c.</hi> It is one property, and piece of <hi>friendſhip</hi> (amongſt others) to give ſome <hi>reception</hi> to friends where they are deſtitute of <hi>Habitation,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Now this is that which is here done by <hi>thoſe Chriſtians</hi> which are relieved, to thoſe that relieved them. Who having engaged them by their liberality doe receive this benefit from them of <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance into Heaven.</hi> This will require a little explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in regard of ſome <hi>difficulty</hi> which is in it. Some there are, who have a conceit with themſelves as if <hi>Chriſt</hi> by deſiring them to make friends of the <hi>mammon of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> did tacitely allow of wealth, which is gotten by <hi>unrighteous Courſes;</hi> or at leaſt that he did ſo far <hi>extinuate</hi> it as that they might <hi>ſatisfie</hi> for the unrighteouſneſſe of it by thoſe <hi>almes</hi> which they beſtowed upon the poor: ſo that when a man hath ſcraped a great deale of wealth together in his life time, by couzenage, and injuſtice, and oppreſſion, and ſuch wayes before named<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo <hi>ſpent</hi> (it may be) a great part of it <hi>among harlots and with riotous living,</hi> as it is noted of the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> that in the mean time it ſerve the turne to ſave him, and to make amends &amp;c. It might in the mean time ſerve the turne to <hi>ſave</hi> him, &amp; to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30513:19"/>make amends for all his <hi>former iniquity,</hi> if when he dyed he gave ſo much away to ſuch and ſuch perſons, which were in want: But this was farr enough from the minde of <hi>our bleſſed Saviour;</hi> who ſpeaks not here of <hi>Mammon</hi> what it ought to be, or may be in the thing it ſelf, but what <hi>it is</hi> as to mens <hi>uſual improvements,</hi> as I hinted in part before, and when theſe friends are ſaid to <hi>receive or bring</hi> men into <hi>everlaſting Habitations,</hi> we are to take it as an <hi>improper</hi> expreſſion by a <hi>Metonymy</hi> of the <hi>effect,</hi> when that is done whereby the other is <hi>conſequent,</hi> and following thereunto. It is <hi>Chriſt alone</hi> who does <hi>proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> receive us into thoſe places whereinto he is gone himſelf, who having the key of <hi>David</hi> does <hi>open</hi> the kingdome of heaven for us and take us to himſelf. But even <hi>others</hi> alſo who are <hi>Chriſtian friends,</hi> are in a <hi>ſenſe</hi> ſaid here to doe it likewiſe, <hi>they</hi> do alſo receive thoſe who have done good unto them into theſe everlaſting Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. And that (as we may take it) according to this following explication.</p>
            <p n="1">I. By their <hi>Prayers,</hi> and Remembrances of them at the <hi>Throne of Grace,</hi> whiles <hi>Rich</hi> men doe beſtow their <hi>Charity</hi> upon the poor Members of Chriſt, they doe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much ingage them, and provoke them to <hi>pray</hi> for them: And to pray for them as to thoſe Concernments, which are <hi>beſt</hi> and moſt expedient for them, which is the <hi>furtherance of their ſalvation.</hi> This ſhall turne to <hi>my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> through the help of your <hi>prayers,</hi> Philip. 1.19. The prayers of Chriſtians for one another, doe very much conduce to their <hi>ſalvation</hi> and eternal advantage, and this is that which is done and which <hi>is</hi> to be done by them. <hi>Pauperis eſt or are; Divitis erogare, Auguſtine.</hi> The <hi>rich</hi> are to <hi>lay</hi> out their <hi>moneys</hi> and the poor their<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30513:20"/>
               <hi>Prayers</hi> thus. 2 Tim. 1.16. <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> he was kinde to St. <hi>Paul</hi> and often refreſhed him, and what followed thereupon? we may ſee in the laſt verſe of that Chapter, <hi>The Lord grant unto him, that he may finde mercy of the Lord in that day:</hi> he promoted his Salvation by his <hi>prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This muſt be taken in its full <hi>latitude</hi> and extent as praying for their Salvation not only in the <hi>end</hi> but in the <hi>meanes:</hi> for the changing of their <hi>hearts;</hi> for the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of their <hi>Natures:</hi> for the ſubduing of their <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> for the beſtowing of the <hi>Grace</hi> of God upon them in all the kinds of it, this is indeed to pray for their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when together with their prayer, there is <hi>a ſupply of the Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> as in the place before cited Philipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans 1.19.</p>
            <p>There are many who when they hear of <hi>going to Heaven</hi> they think to doe it <hi>per ſaltum;</hi> to go thither at one <hi>jump,</hi> to leap preſently from <hi>Dives table</hi> into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's boſome:</hi> that is from the injoyment of their <hi>luſts</hi> to the injoyment of <hi>Happineſse;</hi> and they think ther's no more belongs to it but only for ſo many good men to pray for their ſalvation at <hi>large</hi> and theres an end of it. But alas theres a great deal more then ſo in it, and ſo to be expected. When we ſpeak of the <hi>Salvation</hi> of any perſons, we ſpeak of it in all its intercurrencies, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratories and <hi>intermediations</hi> of ſuch <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>duties</hi> as are tending thereunto: and ſo when we ſpeak of <hi>praying</hi> for their ſalvation; we are to underſtand it in this <hi>method,</hi> and order and connexion, of the diſcovery of their <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition,</hi> of their apprehenſion of the neceſſity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of their willingneſſe to cloſe with him upon his <hi>own terms</hi> Thus do the Saints and ſervants of God, help their friends too heaven by their <hi>Prayers,</hi> not when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30513:20"/>they are out of the world, (it is to late <hi>then</hi> to pray for them) but while they abide ſtill in it.</p>
            <p n="2">II. By their <hi>Council and advice,</hi> by their gracious and ſavory <hi>ſpeeches:</hi> by their pertinent and ſeaſonable <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions,</hi> and provocations to that, which is their <hi>Duty,</hi> they doe hereby further them in this particular, it is not done as by a <hi>charme or ſpel;</hi> but In theſe <hi>holy wayes and meanes:</hi> which God has graciouſly ſanctifyed to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in the <hi>communion of Saints</hi> which having a mixture eſpecially of the Heart and love and <hi>Affection</hi> of theſe good men with it, is very <hi>availeable</hi> in this reſpect.</p>
            <p n="3">III. By their <hi>Teſtimony and Comprobation,</hi> when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall hereafter ſit upon his judgement ſeat at the laſt day, then ſhall theſe his poor members be ready to bear witneſſe to the charity of ſuch men as theſe who have bin liberal to them: I (ſayes one) was <hi>hungry</hi> and this man fed <hi>me,</hi> and I (ſayes another) was <hi>naked</hi> and this man cloathed <hi>me,</hi> and I (ſayes another) was a <hi>ſtranger</hi> and this man <hi>lodged me,</hi> and I (ſayes another) was <hi>ſick</hi> and in <hi>priſon,</hi> and this man <hi>came unto me;</hi> and ſo of the reſt. And what ſhall be the iſſue and conſequent of all this Teſtimony at laſt? why even that which is there ſignified to us. Matth. 25.34. <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdome prepared for you, from the foundation of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. This holds good in a way of <hi>Gratulatory enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment:</hi> thoſe <hi>friends</hi> whom you have made by your <hi>almes</hi> ſhall <hi>receive</hi> you into heaven; ſo farr forth as <hi>any</hi> of them (as it may happen) being there <hi>before</hi> you, ſhall <hi>rejoice</hi> to ſee you come <hi>thither</hi> as indeed they <hi>ſhall.</hi> Look as there is <hi>joy in Heaven</hi> amongſt the <hi>Angels</hi> for any one <hi>ſinner that is converted:</hi> ſo is there joy alſo in Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30513:21"/>amongſt the <hi>Saints</hi> for any one <hi>convert that is glorified,</hi> there is a mutual Heavenly <hi>welcome</hi> which they doe <hi>bid</hi> (as I may ſay) one to another into thoſe <hi>everlasting Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations,</hi> and this is that which you, who have formerly bin bountiful to them ſhall then partake of from them.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this point thus opened and in larged may be thus far uſeful to us, namely: from hence to teach us to ſet an high price and eſtimation upon the poor ſervants of Chriſt, and to think highly &amp; honorably of them. We doe uſually ſo farr reckon of any perſons as they are able to doe the moſt for us, now ſee here by this rule how to account of ſuch perſons as thoſe who are enabled thus to help us to <hi>Heaven,</hi> which is the greateſt good of all, <hi>we</hi> ſhould <hi>honour</hi> them and think <hi>highly</hi> of them in the midſt of many <hi>outward</hi> diſparagements, they are men of great intereſt with <hi>God,</hi> and ſo they ſhould be of great eſteem with <hi>us,</hi> and we ſhould never think we can doe enough for them, nor never <hi>repent</hi> of any good that ever we <hi>did</hi> them as being ſure it ſhall not be <hi>loſt</hi> but abundantly <hi>recompenſed</hi> to us: take heed of deſpiſing one of <hi>theſe little ones,</hi> who have ſuch <hi>great</hi> things in their <hi>reach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea and take heed of <hi>diſingageing</hi> them alſo, and of doing any thing to them whereby to <hi>looſe</hi> or abate of their <hi>affection,</hi> which may be of more uſe unto us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps then we are aware of, not only as to the keeping off of <hi>temporal evils</hi> &amp; calamityes, and the procuring of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>temporal bleſsings;</hi> but alſo as to the diverting of God's <hi>eternal wrath,</hi> and indignation; and admittance into the <hi>everlaſting Habitations.</hi> And thats the <hi>ſecond</hi> thing here intimated, <hi>xiz,</hi> The <hi>practiſe</hi> of the poor releived Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30513:21"/>which they will be ready to comply with in reference to thoſe perſons that relieve them.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt is the <hi>Iſsue,</hi> or effect in regard of the <hi>thing it ſelf,</hi> and that is that theſe <hi>liberal perſons,</hi> who doe lay out of their eſſates to <hi>good uſes:</hi> they ſhall indeed at the laſt have admittance and <hi>entrance into thoſe everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing habitations, They ſhall receive you:</hi> that is no more, but <hi>you ſhall be received:</hi> by taking the words not <hi>relative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſo much as <hi>abſolutely,</hi> nor <hi>perſonally</hi> but <hi>imperſonally</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And this is very ſutable and agreable to other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, where the like <hi>Form</hi> and manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion hath the like ſenſe, and meaning with it; as Luk. 6, 38. Good meaſure ſhall <hi>they</hi> give into your boſome, that is good meaſure <hi>ſhall be given.</hi> Luk. 12.20. This night ſhall <hi>they</hi> take away thy Soul: that is, thy Soul ſhall <hi>be taken away.</hi> And Revel. 12.6. Speaking of <hi>the woman fled into the wilderneſſe;</hi> where ſhe hath a place prepared of God, that <hi>they</hi> ſhould feed her: that is, <hi>that ſhe might be fed,</hi> as will appear if we ſhall compare it with the 14 verſe of that chapter. And ſo now anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able here in the <hi>text, that they</hi> may recieve you, that is (I ſay) that you may <hi>be recieved.</hi> And ſo now it does not ſo much point out the <hi>Perſons;</hi> as rather the <hi>ſtate</hi> and condition it ſelf, not the <hi>Perſons conferring</hi> but rather the ſtate and condition it ſelf, which is conferred. This is the ſumm of all, that thoſe who faithfully expend of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtates to the relief of the poor ſervants of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when they dye they ſhall have <hi>Heaven it ſelf</hi> beſtowed upon them. This is the doctrine of this preſent text and of the whole ſcripture likewiſe beſide: which yet, that it may be duly and rightly underſtood by us, muſt be taken with this explication.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:30513:22"/>
            <p n="1">I. That this is not meant of any <hi>meritorius virtue</hi> in the act of Beneficence it ſelf: ſo that whoſoever ſhall give an Almes more or leſs to any one poor man or more, he ſhall thereby <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and as it were <hi>ex opere operato promeriti</hi> a place in Heaven: for that he <hi>ſhall not</hi> nor <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> doe. There is no proportion or commenſuration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>our</hi> bounty and the bounty of <hi>God</hi> in eternal life.</p>
            <p n="2">II. It is not ſo meant neither; as if this <hi>liberality</hi> were enough of it ſelf for any man that ſhould go to Heaven, with out other graces beſides, for ſo neither it is not. It is not liberality conſidered <hi>ſolitarily or abſtractly,</hi> but in its full <hi>concomitancy:</hi> in the aſſociation of <hi>other good works</hi> going along with it. It is not when ye faile of your <hi>duty,</hi> but when ye faile of your <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. It is not meant neither <hi>Independently</hi> upon the general principle of <hi>ſaving Grace</hi> wrought in the Heart, we are ſaid to be <hi>created</hi> in Chriſt Ieſus unto <hi>good works</hi> that we ſhould walk in them. Eph. 2.10. And it holds good of theſe works of <hi>Beneficence</hi> among the reſt: which are no further properly <hi>good</hi> neither have <hi>Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> attending upon them, then as they flow and proceed in us from ſuch a <hi>root</hi> and ſpring as this: not from a common principle only of <hi>morality,</hi> but from a ſpecial principle of <hi>regeneration</hi> and the <hi>new Creature.</hi> The end of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is <hi>charity:</hi> out of a <hi>pure heart,</hi> and a <hi>good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and of <hi>Faith unfeigned</hi> 1. Tim. 1.5.</p>
            <p>So then the plain and direct meaning is briefly this: That as God will reward <hi>all other</hi> good ſervices beſides with <hi>Eternal life</hi> in a <hi>ſubject</hi> duly <hi>fitted</hi> and qualified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; ſo amongſt the reſt in a <hi>ſpecial</hi> manner will he take notice of the <hi>kindneſse which is done</hi> to any of his poor ſervants, and will at laſt reward that alſo with eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:30513:22"/>
            <p>This is matter of great encouragement to any to be faithful in ſuch performances as theſe, alwaies to <hi>abound</hi> in this work of the Lord; for asmuch as they hear and may know that their <hi>labour ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi> That which makes men commonly ſo ſtrait-handed and cloſe-fiſted towards the poor, is becauſe they have this conceit with themſelves that they ſhall otherwiſe be <hi>looſers</hi> by the bargains. But here now for their comfort it is the <hi>contrary,</hi> if it be <hi>gain</hi> to be partakers of <hi>Heaven,</hi> they ſhall not <hi>looſe</hi> that are bountiful towards the poor.</p>
            <p>And therefore let this argument have its full <hi>force</hi> and efficacy upon us. Thoſe whom God hath bleſt with theſe eſtates, they ſhould be prevailed upon by it, yea, and it is <hi>lawful</hi> for them to be ſo, as is here imply'd. We may <hi>do good</hi> out of the <hi>hopes of Heaven,</hi> and out of reſpect to the <hi>recompence</hi> of the reward as is here ſignifyed to us in the <hi>text.</hi> That which God propounds as an <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> we may make to ourſelves as <hi>an inducement,</hi> and that which he alledges as a <hi>reaſon</hi> to provoke us to <hi>charity,</hi> we may be <hi>wrought</hi> upon to <hi>charity</hi> from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that reaſon in our ſelves. It is true, we are to doe it out of <hi>other</hi> conſiderations <hi>beſides;</hi> out of <hi>Love</hi> to the <hi>performance</hi> it ſelf, wherein we are imploy'd: out of <hi>reſpect</hi> to our poor <hi>Bretheren</hi> whom we relieve, out of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> who <hi>commands</hi> it and requires it at our hands, out of regard to <hi>Chriſt</hi> who <hi>counſels</hi> us, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth us to it: but over and above we may take in this likewiſe out of reſpect to <hi>ourſelves,</hi> who ſhall be <hi>eternally rewarded</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved,</hi> we never know the <hi>worth of goodneſſe,</hi> till we come <hi>to dye</hi> and leave the world, then <hi>grace;</hi> will be <hi>grace,</hi> and religion, <hi>religion,</hi> and goodneſſe goodneſſe <hi>indeed.</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:30513:23"/>When ye <hi>faile, then</hi> ye ſhall <hi>ſee</hi> what it was in the belief of Gods gracious <hi>promiſes</hi> to <hi>obey</hi> his moſt holy <hi>commands,</hi> when ye faile of your <hi>lives,</hi> ye ſhall not then faile of your <hi>expectations,</hi> God will be as good as his <hi>word</hi> and a great deal <hi>better</hi> and will do for his ſervants abundantly <hi>above all that they can ask or think. Eye hath not ſeen nor ear heard, neither hath it entred in to the heart of man to conceive the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9.</p>
            <p>Therefore though our <hi>reward</hi> may be deferr'd for the <hi>preſent</hi> yet it will come at <hi>laſt;</hi> though we ſee it not whiles we <hi>live,</hi> yet we ſhall partake of it at our lives <hi>end;</hi> and though we have it not in <hi>this</hi> world, yet we ſhall not <hi>miſs</hi> of it in the world <hi>to come.</hi> As our Saviour ſpeaks in another place upon the like occaſion. Luke. 14.13, 14. Where he perſwades them to invite the <hi>poor,</hi> the <hi>maimed,</hi> and the <hi>blinde</hi> &amp;c. For this (ſayes he) <hi>Thou ſhalt be bleſt,</hi> and though they cannot <hi>recompence</hi> thee <hi>here</hi> yet they ſhall be an <hi>occaſion</hi> of thy recompence <hi>hereafter, For thou ſhalt be recompenſed at the reſurrection of the juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the <hi>TEXT.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:30513:23"/>
               <p>NOw as for the preſent <hi>Occaſion,</hi> it is (as most here under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand) for the interring of the Corps of a <hi>Gentleman</hi> well known amongst you, by name <hi>WILLIAM A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAMS <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi> ſometime call'd to the place and dignity of <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in this Honourable <hi>City;</hi> a worthy <hi>Member</hi> of the Right Worſhipfull Company of <hi>Haberdaſhers,</hi> and an ancient <hi>Inhabitant</hi> of this Pariſh in which we now are. Of whom there are many <hi>Good</hi> things, which I am able upon mine <hi>own</hi> knowledge and many yeares <hi>acquaintance</hi> with him to relate in his just commendation. But I ſhall endeavour to contract them all into as cloſe a room as may be, that I may not ſeem tedious to You, yet ſomewhat I muſt needs ſay, for <hi>Imitation,</hi> and the incouragement of <hi>others,</hi> that they may not looſe the Benefit of ſo noble and rare an <hi>Example:</hi> For <hi>Examples</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch as we are accountable for to <hi>God</hi> as well as <hi>Rules;</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it not altogether improper or impertinent to the work of our <hi>Miniſtery</hi> to unfold them, and lay them open before you with the beſt advantage. I could tell you of his great <hi>Integrity</hi> and plaine-heartedneſſe and freedome from <hi>guile;</hi> of his <hi>Humility,</hi> and Modesty, and Meekneſs, and Lowlineſſe of Minde; neither highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of <hi>Himſelf,</hi> nor yet affecting the Applauſe of <hi>others,</hi> of his diligent attendance upon the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and his Love to <hi>good Men,</hi> of his <hi>pitifull</hi> and compaſſionate Affection upon occaſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Calamities: But that which I ſhall chiefly inſiſt on, as which is most <hi>proper</hi> and pertinent, is to ſhew you how good a <hi>Parallel</hi> and Correſpondency he held with the <hi>Text,</hi> which we have now diſcust, and how well he put in <hi>practice</hi> this counſel of our Bleſſed Saviour which He gives to <hi>Rich</hi> Men.</p>
               <p>God had blest him with a very fair Estate here in the world, which was not in regard of <hi>Him</hi> the Mammon of <hi>Iniquity;</hi> but indeed the fruit of <hi>Induſtry,</hi> not purchas'd by <hi>fraud,</hi> or injury, or oppreſſion (as ſometimes it is) but by a diligent and <hi>laborious hand,</hi> which hath <hi>in Scripture</hi> the <hi>promiſe</hi> of Riches made unto it.</p>
               <p>He was not <hi>ſuddenly</hi> rich, as one that made <hi>haſte</hi> thereunto, (as <hi>Solomon</hi> complains of <hi>ſome</hi>) which is oftentimes very <hi>ſuſpicious,</hi> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:30513:24"/>ſeldome <hi>proſperous;</hi> but he came up to his Estate by <hi>degrees,</hi> and leiſurable proceedings, wherein He might diſcern the hand of God going along with him, and aſſiſtant to him. And when he came to have an <hi>Eſtate</hi> conſiderable, his <hi>Charity</hi> and deſire of doing good grew up with it, and as our Saviour here adviſes, he began to think with himſelf of making him Friends therewith, which he did in great Abundance.</p>
               <p>His Firſt Care was that which the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, <hi>1 Timoth. 5.4, 8.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. To ſhew <hi>piety at home,</hi> and <hi>to take care of his own Relations.</hi> He was mindfull and carefull of <hi>that.</hi> And foraſmuch as being a <hi>Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> he was destitute of thoſe more <hi>direct</hi> and neerer Relations of <hi>Wife and Children,</hi> his Bounty ſpread it ſelf forth to his <hi>Collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Branches, for whoſe ſake it is to be thought he was the willinger to deny himſelf the <hi>Comfort</hi> of thoſe other <hi>Dependances.</hi> And he was exceeding <hi>large</hi> and ample in his proviſions for them in <hi>every</hi> reſpect, both in <hi>educating</hi> them ſuitably to their proper <hi>diſpoſitions</hi> and inclinations; and afterwards being <hi>grovvn up</hi> and fitted for further Improvements, in perfecting theſe Beginnings to them. In that he very prudently and bountifully <hi>ſtock'd</hi> ſome, <hi>match'd</hi> others, and <hi>follovved</hi> them with his continual <hi>advice,</hi> and other aſſiſtance. One of them amongſt the reſt I cannot but take notice of <hi>eſpecially,</hi> whom he brought up in <hi>Learning,</hi>
                  <note n="*">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Walter Adams B. D <hi>ſometime</hi> Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>of</hi> Emmanuel-Colledge <hi>in</hi> Camb. <hi>and now</hi> Miniſter <hi>of</hi> Hampſted <hi>neer</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> first at the <hi>Grammar-School</hi> here in <hi>London,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> and ſince that being ſetled in the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> hath followed him with further incouragements, wherein his <hi>Coſt</hi> was not <hi>Ill</hi> bestowed; God bleſſing him with the Comfortable <hi>Succeſs</hi> of all his <hi>Love</hi> in that particular.</p>
               <p>Having thus comfortably and plentifully provided for his own Relations, and ſhown piety at <hi>home,</hi> his next care was of the <hi>publick</hi> and doing <hi>good abroad:</hi> for which purpoſe after good and ſerious and very <hi>private</hi> advice taken with ſuch friends as were fit to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted in ſuch a buſineſſe, he pitched upon a deſign of founding a free grammer School at <hi>Newport</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> the place of his Nativity, where he erected a large fabrick, for the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:30513:24"/>of <hi>fourſcore</hi> Schollars (gratis) born in the ſaid <hi>Town,</hi> or living within <hi>three</hi> miles compaſs thereabout. A large <hi>library</hi> over the ſaid School: and alſo two fair <hi>houſes</hi> thereunto adjoyning for the two <hi>Schoolemaſters</hi> therein to <hi>inhabit;</hi> together with <hi>Gardens</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> appertaining. He likewiſe ſetled lands of about <hi>ten</hi> pounds <hi>per annum</hi> for the teaching of children in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſchoole to fit them for the <hi>Latine</hi> Grammer-ſchoole.</p>
               <p>He built four commodious <hi>Almes-houſes</hi> fronting the Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of the ſaid ſchoole towards the street, and likewiſe ſettled a yearly: maintainance upon the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the ſaid town for the yearly <hi>Catechizing</hi> of the ſaid ſchollars and <hi>other</hi> youths.</p>
               <p>He ſetled <hi>exhibitions</hi> for the maintainance of <hi>four</hi> poor ſchollers of his Foundation at the <hi>Vniverſity:</hi> and alſo yearly to clothe and put forth to be apprentices <hi>four</hi> poor youthes to convenient <hi>Trades.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He made proviſion for the constant <hi>repaires</hi> of the ſaid ſchoole, and Almes-Houſes, and for other conveniences belonging there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, all which in his life time he ſaw fully effected, and did him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf amply endow with good lands there <hi>adjacent.</hi> He obtained a <hi>Confirmation</hi> of the ſettlement thereof, and of the prudent <hi>Statutes</hi> for the Government of the ſaid Schoole by Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to law.</p>
               <p>He hath moreover taken order that after his <hi>Deceaſe</hi> there ſhould be built a fair <hi>Market-houſe</hi> with a <hi>Town-hall</hi> over it in the ſaid Town of <hi>Newport:</hi> for the effecting whereof he hath made ample proviſion.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, he hath by his last <hi>will and teſtament</hi> given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Chriſts</hi> Hoſpital (where he was <hi>a governour</hi>) an <hi>hundred and fifty</hi> pounds. To the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Pariſh</hi> of St. <hi>Lawrence-Jury</hi> (where he had lived for many yeares) an <hi>hundred and twenty</hi> pounds. To <hi>ten</hi> poor Miniſters widdows <hi>five</hi> pounds a piece. To <hi>tvventy</hi> poor men of the <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi> Company <hi>tvventy</hi> ſhillings a piece yearly <hi>for</hi> ever. And to the ſame worthy Company (whereof <hi>himſelf</hi> had bin an Ancient <hi>member</hi>) he left friendly <hi>memorials</hi> of his reſpect. In whom likewiſe he repoſed the <hi>TRVST</hi> of all his former ſettlements, and made them the <hi>viſitors</hi> and <hi>overſeers</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with due allowance for defraying the charges concerning the ſame.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30513:25"/>
               <p>When the aforeſaid <hi>Schooles</hi> were finiſhed, and indowed, and two able and eminent Schoolemaſters ſetled therein, and the Schollers grown numerous, which was in a very <hi>ſhort</hi> time; An account com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his hands of thoſe great hopes which the <hi>viſitors</hi> and <hi>School-maſters</hi> conceiv'd of much happineſſe that the <hi>Foundation</hi> promiſed both to <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>future</hi> Ages, He with <hi>Tears</hi> uttered theſe words, or to the like effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>That he had great cauſe to bleſſe God vvho had intruſted him vvith ſuch an eſtate, but much greater cauſe to bleſs him for give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him an heart to diſpoſe it in a vvay that might conduce to Gods glory, and the good of his country.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>After all this his coſt labour and travail, which was great and of long continuance, he hath by his laſt <hi>vvill and teſtament</hi> with ſo much wiſdome, love, and impartiallity, bequeathed a very fair estate among all his relations and other friends, as that it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved theres not one of them, but reſts abundantly and thankfully ſatisfied. Ther's many a man that in dividing his estate divides alſo his <hi>friends,</hi> whom he divides that estate unto, and does not make <hi>friends</hi> but <hi>Enemies</hi> of the Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe. But it was his happineſs to doe the quite <hi>contrary,</hi> he did not hereby <hi>divide</hi> his friends but rather <hi>unite</hi> them: and not only make them friends to <hi>himſelf,</hi> but alſo <hi>one</hi> to <hi>another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God blest him with a <hi>long life,</hi> which in it ſelf is a <hi>great</hi> bleſſing, and accordingly both to be <hi>accounted</hi> and <hi>improved,</hi> he was an <hi>old</hi> man, and <hi>full of daies,</hi> about <hi>fourſcore</hi> yeares of Age &amp; (which made it ſo much the longer) free from thoſe <hi>Infirmities</hi> which old Age is ſubject unto and oftentimes incumbred withall; God make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good that <hi>promiſe</hi> to him, which is <hi>conditionally</hi> made to a good and righteous perſon. <hi>Job. 5.26.</hi> Thou ſhalt <hi>come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhock of corne cometh in it's ſeaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let thoſe whom God hath bleſt with ſuch opportunities as he <hi>had</hi> be careful all they can to improve them as he <hi>did,</hi> that ſo making to themſelves <hi>friends of this Mammon of unrighteouſneſſe</hi> they may at laſt be received into thoſe <hi>everlaſting Habitations,</hi> which God hath prepared for all <hi>that love his appearing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 25. lin. 2. read <hi>not to know whither.</hi> pag. 28. dele lin. penult. <hi>in ſome Copies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30513:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
